# **Felipe CADAR**

eucadar.com | LinkedIn | Scholar | GitHub

Email: felipecadarchamone@gmail.com, cadar@dcc.ufmg.br

#### **PHD STUDENT**

I am a computer science Ph.D. student at the Federal University of Minas Gerais (UFMG), Brazil, and a visiting Ph.D. student at Université de Bourgogne, France. I have been doing research at the Laboratory of Computer Vision and Robotics (VeRLab) since I joined the CS undergrad program in the first semester of 2016. I really enjoy doing research and would love to see my work positively impact someone's life.

#### **EDUCATION**

Université de Bourgogne

Dijon, France

Location: Dijon, France

Doctorant Invité

Hosts: Cédric Demonceaux and Renato Martins

May. 2023 - Today

Nov. 2021 - Today

Research Focus: Semantic-Aware Feature Description and Matching

Research rocus. Semantic Aware reature Description and M

Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais

Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil

Ph.D., Computer Science

Advisors: Erickson R. Nascimento and Renato Martins

Research Focus: Computer Vision and Machine Learning - Local Image Features

In 2 years, results published at CVIU 2022, CVPR 2023 and PRL 2023.

Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais

Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil Feb. 2016 – Nov. 2021

B.Sc., Computer Science

Advisor: Erickson R. Nascimento

While in graduation, I took part in several papers in prestige venues, like CVPR, ICCV, and NeurIPS

### RELEVANT RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## Google AI Research Internship

Oct. 2022 – Dec. 2022

Google Research

Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil

- This project was an intersection between Computer Vision and Natural Language Processing.
- Trained memory augmented models on new datasets and achieved state-of-the-art results.
- Co-author in one ICCV publication.

## **Nonrigid Local Features**

June 2018 – Today

VeRLab

UFMG, Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil

- Development of visual descriptors for matching nonrigid objects.
- Collected and annotated 2 real world datasets publicly available to the community.
- Co-author in 4 publication in ICCV, CVIU, NeurIPS, and CVPR 2023.
  More info in https://www.verlab.dcc.ufmg.br/descriptors/

#### **Semantic Hyperlapse**

April 2016 – Sep. 2018

VeRLab

UFMG, Belo Horizonte, MG, Brazil

- Helped developing a semantic fast-forward method for first-person videos to emphasize important parts while maintaining smooth motion.
- Collected a large multimodal dataset with first person videos.
- Co-author in a CVPR publication

More info in https://www.verlab.dcc.ufmg.br/semantic-hyperlapse/

#### **AWARDS & HONORS**

- ICCV grant to attend the conference France Aug. 2023
- CAPES Scholarship for visiting PhD Student in Université de Bourgogne France Dec. 2022
- 18th place of 642 teams in Kaggle competition: Google Image Matching Challenge 2022 Jun. 2022

## **SERVICE TO THE COMMUNITY**

- I was a reviewer at CVPR 2023, ICCV 2023, and 3DV 2024
- I promoted a workshop at the Google's Mind the Gap 2018 event "Programming for HoloLens"
- I volunteer for UFMG's "Mostra sua UFMG" to help high school students choose a course

## **JOURNAL ARTICLES**

- <u>F. Cadar</u>, W. Melo, V. Kanagasabapathi, G. Potje, R. Martins, and E. Nascimento (2023). "Improving the matching of deformable objects by learning to detect keypoints". In: *Pattern Recognition Letters*, *PRL*. DOI: 10.1016/j.patrec.2023.08.012.
- Potje, G., R. Martins, <u>F. Cadar</u>, and E. Nascimento (2022). "Learning geodesic-aware local features from RGB-D images". In: *Computer Vision and Image Understanding*, **CVIU**. DOI: 10.1016/j.cviu.2022.103409.
- Silva, M., W. Ramos, <u>F. Cadar</u>, J. Ferreira, M. Campos, and E. Nascimento (2018). "Making a long story short: A multi-importance fast-forwarding egocentric videos with the emphasis on relevant objects". In: *Journal of Visual Communication and Image Representation*, **JVCI**. DOI: 10.1016/j.jvcir.2018.02.013.
- Silva, S., <u>F. Cadar</u>, R. Ferreira, and E. Nascimento (2018). "A 3D modeling methodology based on a concavity-aware geometric test to create 3D textured coarse models from concept art and orthographic projections". In: *Computers and Graphics*, *CAG*. DOI: 10.1016/j.cag.2018.09.002.

## **CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS**

- Mensink, Thomas, Jasper Uijlings, Lluis Castrejon, Arushi Goel, <u>F. Cadar</u>, Howard Zhou, Fei Sha, André Araujo, and Vittorio Ferrari (2023). "Encyclopedic VQA: Visual questions about detailed properties of fine-grained categories". In: *IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision, ICCV*.
- Potje, G., <u>F. Cadar</u>, A. Araujo, R. Martins, and E. R. Nascimento (2023). "Enhancing Deformable Local Features by Jointly Learning to Detect and Describe Keypoints". In: *Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition*, **CVPR**.
- Potje, G., R. Martins, <u>F. Cadar</u>, and E. R. Nascimento (2021). "Extracting Deformation-Aware Local Features by Learning to Deform". In: *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems*, *NeurIPS*. URL: https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2021/file/5934c1ec0cd31e12bd9084d106bc2e32-Paper.pdf.
- Nascimento, E., G. Potje, R. Martins, <u>F. Cadar</u>, M. Campos, and R. Bajcsy (2019). "GEOBIT: A geodesic-based binary descriptor invariant to non-rigid deformations for RGB-D images". In: *IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision*, *ICCV*. DOI: 10.1109/ICCV.2019.01010.
- Rezeck, P., <u>F. Cadar</u>, J. Soares, B. Frade, L. Pinto, H. Azpurua, D. Macharet, L. Chaimowicz, G. Freitas, and M. Campos (2018). "An immersion enhancing robotic head-like device for teleoperation". In: *15th Latin American Robotics Symposium*, *LARS*. DOI: 10.1109/LARS/SBR/WRE.2018.00038.
- Rezeck, P., B. Frade, J. Soares, L. Pinto, <u>F. Cadar</u>, H. Azpurua, D. Macharet, L. Chaimowicz, G. Freitas, and M. Campos (2018). "Framework for haptic teleoperation of a remote robotic arm device". In: *15th Latin American Robotics Symposium*, *LARS*. DOI: 10.1109/LARS/SBR/WRE.2018.00039.
- Silva, M., W. Ramos, J. Ferreira, <u>F. Cadar</u>, M. Campos, and E.R. Nascimento (2018). "A Weighted Sparse Sampling and Smoothing Frame Transition Approach for Semantic Fast-Forward First-Person Videos". In: *Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition*, **CVPR**. DOI: 10.1109/CVPR.2018.00253.